DC Oral History Collaborative Collection 180
People's Archive, MLK Library
DC Oral History Collaborative Collection
2016
People's Archive, MLK Library
180
100 Gigabytes
Scope and Contents
D.C. Oral History Collaborative (DCOHC) is a citywide initiative to train community members in oral history skills, fund new and ongoing oral history projects, connect volunteers with oral history projects, and publicize existing oral history collections. DCOHC is a project of DC Public Library, HumanitiesDC, and the Historical Society of Washington, D.C. This collection contains oral history interviews, transcripts, and indexes produced by DCOHC grantees.
Oral History; Digital materials; Audio; Video recordings
- Series 1: Whitman-Walker Health Oral History Project
  Biographical / Historical
  Whitman-Walker Health, formerly Whitman-Walker Clinic, is a non-profit community health center in the Washington, DC metropolitan area that specializes in HIV/AIDS treatment and LGBTQ healthcare. Founded as an affirming health center for the gay and lesbian community in 1978, Whitman-Walker was one of the first responders to the HIV/AIDS epidemic in DC and became a leader in HIV/AIDS education, prevention, diagnosis and treatment. In recent years, Whitman-Walker has expanded its services to include primary healthcare services, a stronger focus on queer women's care, and youth services.
  Scope and Contents
  The Whitman-Walker Health Oral History Collection contains 10 audio interviews of members of the Whitman-Walker community. The interviews were conducted by Hannah Byrne and Jewel Addy in late 2017 and early 2018 to celebrate the 40th Anniversay of Whitman-Walker Health. Transcripts are included for all interviews.
  Reproductive health services; HIV (Viruses); Families; LGBTQ people -- GLBTQ people
  - Sub-Series 1: Interviews
    - Barbara Lewis interview, 2017-08-17; dcpl_dcohc001_01.wav
      Barbara Lewis is a healthcare professional, longtime Whitman-Walker Clinic volunteer, and current Physician Assistant at Whitman-Walker Health.
      Barbara Lewis discusses her healthcare background, her relationship with Whitman-Walker, and HIV/AIDS in Washington, DC.
    - Carl Corbin interview (part 1 of 2), 2017-08-17; dcpl_dcohc001_02.wav
      Carl Corbin is a patient and former Patient Advisory Committee member at Whitman Walker.
      Carl Corbin dIscusses his background, coming to terms with his HIV diagnosis, his relationship with Whitman-Walker, and HIV/AIDS in Washington, DC.
    - Carl Corbin interview (part 2 of 2), 2017-08-17; dcpl_dcohc001_03.wav
      Carl Corbin further dIscusses his background, coming to terms with his HIV diagnosis, his relationship with Whitman-Walker, and HIV/AIDS in Washington, DC.
    - D Magrini interview (part 1 of 2), 2017-09-27; dcpl_dcohc001_04.wav
      D Magrini is the Community Committment and Training Coordinator at Whitman-Walker.
      D Magrini discusses growing up in Washington, DC, her military service, her previous non-monogamous marriage, power lifting, the emergence of HIV in DC in the 1980s, and her work in Lesbian healthcare.
    - D Magrini interview (part 2 of 2), 2017-10-15; dcpl_dcohc001_05.wav
      D Magrini further discusses growing up in Washington, DC, her military service, her previous non-monogamous marriage, power lifting, the emergence of HIV in DC in the 1980s, and her work in Lesbian healthcare.
    - Derrick "Strawberry" Cox interview, 2017-07-23; dcpl_dcohc001_06.wav
      Derrick "Strawberry" Cox is an LGBT activist and patient at Whitman-Walker.
      Derrick "Strawberry" Cox discusses his background, how he came to use the services at Whitman-Walker, and HIV/AIDS in Washington, DC.
    - Gerard Tyler interview, 2017-11-19; dcpl_dcohc001_07.wav
      Gerard Tyler is a patient mentor and longtime volunteer at Whitman-Walker's Gay Men's Health and Wellness Clinic.
      Gerard Tyler discusses growing up in Fairfax Village, being a mentor at Whitman-Walker, his work with Whitman-Walker's STP clinic, his menengitis diagnosis, and HIV/AIDS in Washington, DC.
    - Joanne Sincero interview, 2017-11-13; dcpl_dcohc001_08.wav
      Joanne Sincero is a Welless Coordinator at Whitman-Walker.
      Joanne Sincero discusses her work with the Lesbian Services Program at Whitman-Walker, her transitiion to a full time position with Whitman-Walker, the joys of a queer-friendly workplace, and HIV/AIDS in Washington, DC.
    - Kermit Turner interview, 2017-09-20; dcpl_dcohc001_09.wav
      Kermit Turner is a longtime patient at Whitman-Walker.
      Kermit Turner discusses his childhood in Annapolis, MD, being the first African American page at Anne Arundel County Public Library, moving to Boston, his return to DC, his HIV diagnosis, his relationship with Whitman-Walker, and his Lymphoma diagnosis and subsequent treatment.
    - Shawn Henderson interview, 2017-11-27; dcpl_dcohc001_10.wav
      Shawn Henderson is an artist and longtime patient at Whitman-Walker.
      Shawn Henderson discusses his life in Virginia and Washington, DC, his love for sports, parenthood, his religious upbringing, living with HIV, and his experiences at Whitman-Walker as a patient.
  - Sub-Series 2: Transcripts
    - Barbara Lewis transcript, 2017-09-15; dcpl_dcohc001_01_tra.pdf
    - Carl Corbin transcript (part 1 of 2), 2017-09-28; dcpl_dcohc001_02_tra.pdf
    - Carl Corbin transcript (part 2 of 2), 2017-09-28; dcpl_dcohc001_03_tra.pdf
    - D Magrini transcript (part 1 of 2), 2017-11-08; dcpl_dcohc001_04_tra.pdf
    - D Magrini transcript (part 2 of 2), 2017-11-08; dcpl_dcohc001_05_tra.pdf
    - Derrick "Strawberry" Cox transcript, 2017-09-05; dcpl_dcohc001_06_tra.pdf
    - Gerard Tyler transcript, 2017-11-27; dcpl_dcohc001_07_tra.pdf
    - Joanne Sincero transcript, 2017-11-20; dcpl_dcohc001_08_tra.pdf
    - Kermit Turner transcript, 2017-09-28; dcpl_dcohc001_09_tra.pdf
    - Shawn Henderson transcript, 2017-11-26; dcpl_dcohc001_10_tra.pdf
- Series 2: Mount Pleasant Riot Oral History Project
  Mount Pleasant is a neighborhood in Ward 1 of Washington, D.C., and is bordered by Adams Morgan, Columbia Heights, and Cleveland Park. In 1991, rioting was sparked in the neighborhood by the shooting of a Salvadoran man by an African American police officer. These interviews touch on memories of the riots, community-police relations, the history of Mount Pleasant, gentrification, and how the neighborhood changed in response to the events of 1991.
  The Mount Pleasant Riot Oral History Collection contains 10 audio interviews of people who were members of the Mount Pleasant, D.C. community during the riot of 1991. The interviews were conducted by Pat Scallen in late 2017 and early 2018. Transcripts are included for all interviews.
  Riots; Mount Pleasant (Washington, D.C.); Racism; Police
  - Sub-Series 1: Interviews
    - Alice Kelly interview, 2018-01-10; dcpl_dcohc002_01.wav
      Alice Kelly has lived on Lamont Street in Mt. Pleasant since 1983. She has been actively involved in the neighborhood since, serving as chair of the local Advisory Neighborhood Commission (ANC) as well as working with Historic Mt. Pleasant, Mt. Pleasant Main Street, the Mt. Pleasant Business Association, and the DC Latino Civil Rights Task Force. Ms Kelly has headed the policy office of the District Department of Transportation for the past 14 years.
      Alice Kelly discusses her initial move to Mount Pleasant, her original impressions of the neighborhood, the improvements at the local elementary school, community efforts to improve the main street, her involvement with the ANC, and the Mount Pleasant riot.
    - Arturo Griffiths interview, 2018-01-04; dcpl_dcohc002_02.wav
      Arturo Griffiths is a longtime resident of Mt. Pleasant and community activist. Born in Panama, he attended DC public schools from grade school through high school and studied at Howard University. He is a co-founder of the Latin American Youth Center and has worked in a variety of capacities organizing in the past several decades. Currently he runs Trabajadores Unidos, an organization which supports day laborers in the Washington, DC region.
      Arturo Griffiths discusses his childhood in Panama, his family's move to DC, learning English, attending Howard University, his political awakening, DC's latino community, Mayor Barry's relationship with the latino community, the ways in which the 1991 riot affected latinos in Mount Pleasant, and the effects of gentrification in the neighborhood.
    - Charlene Howard interview, 2017-10-31; dcpl_dcohc002_03.wav
      Charlene Howard is a longtime Mt. Pleasant resident who lives in the same house that she grew up in on Hobart St NW. Her household is one of the few remaining multi-generational African American families in the neighborhood. She fondly recalls her formative childhood and adolescent years in Mt. Pleasant and reflects upon their importance in shaping her personal values and understanding of the importance of community and diversity. Charlene returned to Hobart St to raise her children and remains actively engaged in local affairs.
      Charlene Howard discusses her childhood in Adams Morgan, the political activism of Mount Pleasant residents in the 1970s, drug use in Washington DC, police-community language barriers, her memories of the Mount Pleasant riot, and gentrification of the neighborhood.
    - Elinor Hart interview, 2017-11-10; dcpl_dcohc002_04.wav
      Elinor Hart has been a homeowner on Hobart St. in Mt. Pleasant since 1974. During this time she has worked closely with the Mt. Pleasant Main Street Association and Historic Mt. Pleasant. Ms Hart has a strong interest in affordable housing and currently coordinates a school partnership for the Washington Lawyers Committee for Civil Rights and Urban Affairs in addition to promoting statehood for Washington, DC.
      Elinor Hart discusses moving to Mount Pleasant in 1974, changing demographics of the neighborhood, the controversy of the neighborhood's Historic District designation, her memories of the 1991 riot, police-community relations, and gentrification.
    - José "Chico" Diaz interview, 2017-12-15; dcpl_dcohc002_05.wav
      José (Chico) Diaz has been affiliated with the Latin American Youth Center (LAYC) for over two decades as a participant in its youth programs and later as an employee. As a child in El Salvador, Mr. Diaz battled polio while living in a zone of conflict between guerrilla and military forces. He arrived in Washington, DC, attended DC public schools, and has since made the District his home. Mr. Diaz is the Director of Information Technology at LAYC.
      José Diaz discusses moving to the US at age 15, his recovery from polio, Mount Pleasant in the 1980s, tensions between latino and african-american youth, the Mount Pleasant riot, and community-police relations.
    - José Sueiro interview, 2017-11-25; dcpl_dcohc002_06.wav
      José Sueiro has lived in Adams Morgan and has been intimately involved in the Washington, DC Latino community since the 1970s. He has worked with area youth as Executive Director of the Latin American Youth Center and as a soccer coach at local high schools. Mr. Sueiro is also the unofficial scribe of the Latino community, having edited several local newspapers (both in Spanish and in English) focused on DC's Latino community. He worked in city government under Mayor Anthony Williams and currently consults with Metro DC Hispanic Contractors Association while running a blog on local Latino affairs, metrodiversity.com.
      José Sueiro discusses his studies at GW university, his move to Panama, his return to DC, his start in the newspaper industry and work at El Latino, DC police's lack of experience with latino youth, his memories of the Mount Pleasant riot, and Mayor Barry's close relationship to the latino community in DC.
    - Mark Poletunow interview, 2017-11-18; dcpl_dcohc002_07.wav
      Mark Poletunow served the Latino community in DC for over two decades as a Capuchin friar. During this time, he worked at the Capilla Latina (now Our Lady Queen of the Americas Catholic parish), served as associate pastor at the Shrine of the Sacred Heart, coordinated Hispanic Catholic catechism for the Archdiocese of Washington, and was the Executive Director of the Hispanic Catholic Center. Mr. Poletunow currently is president of the Malvern Retreat Center in Malvern, PA.
      Mark Poletunow discusses his arrival in DC, teaching English as a second language to Spanish-speaking people, identification with immigrant communities, his work at the Spanish Catholic Center, poor treatment of the latino community by DC police, his memories of the Mount Pleasant riot and their aftermath.
    - Pedro Avilés interview, 2017-11-15; dcpl_dcohc002_08.wav
      Pedro Avilés is a Salvadoran American and a longtime resident of Mt. Pleasant. He has worked closely with and has represented the Latino community in Washington, DC in a variety of positions, including serving as a founding member and the executive director of the DC Latino Civil Rights Task Force. Mr. Avilés is an organizational development specialist who has consulted for the Congressional Hispanic Caucus Institute, the World Bank, the government of El Salvador, and a variety of non-profit agencies.
      Pedro Avilés discusses moving to Adams Morgan in 1974, his memories of Mount Pleasant, his involvement with the Sacred Heart Church Theatre Group, racial identity, tensions between teachers at DC Public Schools and non-English-speaking students, his memories of the Mount Pleasant riot, his subsequent involvement with DC's Latino Task Force, and police-community relations in DC.
    - Robert Fleming interview, 2017-10-30; dcpl_dcohc002_09.wav
      Robert Fleming is a longtime resident and homeowner in Mt. Pleasant. He moved into the neighborhood in 1975 and from the beginning was intimately involved in neighborhood affairs. He served three terms as an ANC commissioner during the 1980s and co-founded Neighbors Consejo, a local community organization that provided bilingual rehabilitation services to indigent alcoholics. Mr. Fleming has organized workshops on home security and street safety for women and is a founding board member of the Mount Pleasant Village, a mutual support organization for seniors.
      Robert Fleming discusses moving to Mount Pleasant, his struggle with alcohol, his involvement in the Mount Pleasant ANC, his memories of the Mount Pleasant riot, gentrification, public intoxication, the improvements in community policing in the neighborhood after the riot, and inter-community relations in Mount Pleasant.
    - Suann Hecht interview, 2017-11-17; dcpl_dcohc002_10.wav
      Suann Hecht is a social worker and community activist who has worked with at-risk youth in Washington, DC for 22 years. Known affectionately as Mama Suann during her time at the Latin American Youth Center's Drop-in Center, Ms Hecht has since devoted her efforts to working with juveniles in detention centers and as wards of the city. She retired in 2017 and spends her time between Columbia Heights and Latin America.
      Suann Hecht discusses moving from New York City to a group house in Mount Pleasant in 1972, her memories of the neighborhood, her involvement with the Latin America Youth Center, the city's handling of the Mount Pleasant riot, the demographics of the neighborhood, and the aftermath of the riot.
  - Sub-Series 2: Transcripts
    - Alice Kelly transcript, 2018-02-02; dcpl_dcohc002_01_tra.pdf
    - Arturo Griffiths transcript, 2018-02-09; dcpl_dcohc002_02_tra.pdf
    - Charlene Howard transcript, 2018-01-25; dcpl_dcohc002_03_tra.pdf
    - Elinor Hart transcript, 2018-01-25; dcpl_dcohc002_04_tra.pdf
    - José "Chico" Diaz transcript, 2018-02-02; dcpl_dcohc002_05_tra.pdf
    - José Sueiro transcript, 2018-02-08; dcpl_dcohc002_06_tra.pdf
    - Mark Poletunow transcript, 2018-01-27; dcpl_dcohc002_07_tra.pdf
    - Pedro Avilés transcript, 2018-02-09; dcpl_dcohc002_08_tra.pdf
    - Robert Fleming transcript, 2018-01-24; dcpl_dcohc002_09_tra.pdf
    - Suann Hecht transcript, 2018-01-26; dcpl_dcohc002_10_tra.pdf
- Series 3: Buzzard Point Oral History Project
  Buzzard Point is an industrial area in Washington D.C. that is currently being redeveloped. It will be the site of the largest PEPCO substation in the city and the new D.C. United soccer stadium, as well as new high-rise condominiums and retail. These oral history interviews document family history in the neighborhood and experiences with pollution and gentrification.
  The Buzzard Point Oral History Collection contains 9 audio interviews of residents of the Buzzard Point, D.C. community. The interviews were conducted by Jesse Card in 2017. Transcripts are included for all interviews.
  Buzzard Point (Washington, D.C.); Community development, Urban; Neighborhood associations; Gentrification
  - Sub-Series 1: Interviews
    - Linda Brown Interview, 2017-07-25; dcpl_dcohc003_01.mp3
      Linda is a native Washingtonian, growing up and spending much of her adult life in Northwest Washington, DC in/around Columbia Heights and attending McKinley Technical High School in Eckington, Northeast Washington, DC. She has lived in public housing in Southwest for 10 years, currently at Greenleaf Senior with her daughter, Chaya. Much of Linda's adult life has been defined by her role as a caretaker for Chaya and the struggles that has necessitated due to historical inadequacies in DC disability services. Linda is active in advocating for increased disability services, organizing opportunities and activities for youth through the Southwest Neighborhood Assembly, and, more recently, in organizing for increased housing rights for disadvantaged and low-income families through Empower DC.
      Linda Brown discusses growing up in Washington, DC and moving to Southwest; the experience of raising her daughter, Chaya, a child with disabilities, and their relationship with the community; her role as an advocate for people with disabilities and her involvement with several organizations, such as TASH, University Legal Services, and Empower DC; public housing; and the redevelopment and historical value of the Southwest neighborhood.
    - Carolyn Mitchell Interview, 2017-08-07; dcpl_dcohc003_02.mp3
      Carolyn came to DC from Detroit, MI in 2004. She works for the American Society of Landscape Architects and spent much of her time since moving to DC helping to develop community-led visions for the future of development in Southwest. Like many Southwest residents, she has become disenchanted with the process and promises of public participation programs, feeling that officials consistently ignore the plans she and other community members create, opting instead for development initiatives that hurt rather than help residents who currently live in the neighborhoods near the Buzzard Point industrial area.
      Carolyn Mitchell discusses moving to Washington, DC and her time spent living in Southwest; her work with the American Society of Landscape Architects; changes and issues within the Southwest neighborhood; her involvement in the community and experience working with local organizations; and gentrification and redevelopment throughout Southwest.
    - Vanessa Ruffin-Colbert Interview, 2017-08-22; dcpl_dcohc003_03.mp3
      Vanessa is a native Washingtonian, living much of her life in Southwest in the very home in which she was born. She has always been very active in her community and has come to be a significant point of access for community members to public officials and offices to ensure public services are benefitting residents of Southwest DC. She has also been passionate about expanding access to and involvement in the arts.
      Vanessa Ruffin-Colbert discusses her early life in Washington, DC and experience living in Southwest; her involvement in the community and relationship with the children and families in the area; changes and issues related to the neighborhood and its residents; redevelopment and construction in Southwest; and her continued efforts and hopes to improve the community.
    - Ryan Pierce Interview, 2017-08-28; dcpl_dcohc003_04.mp3
      Ryan is a young professional living in Southwest DC for three and a half years. He works for the National Park Service and volunteers on the History Task Force of the Southwest Neighborhood Assembly. In this interview he discusses what makes DC a great place to live while addressing the many challenges associated with development, gentrification, and access to public resources.
      Ryan Pierce discusses moving to Washington, DC; his educational background and work related to historic preservation; the history and architecture of Southwest; his involvement with the Southwest Neighborhood Assembly (SWNA) and its History Task Force; redevelopment and gentrification in the area, as well as residents' input and responses to these changes; and his thoughts on the future of the neighborhood.
    - Brian Hamilton Interview, 2017-09-06; dcpl_dcohc003_05.mp3
      Brian—along with his wife, Ruth—is a co-pastor of the Westminster Presbyterian Church in Southwest DC. He has lived and worked in the community for 21 years and is passionate about improving community relations and the social and economic conditions of Southwest residents. In this interview he provides a lot of historical analysis to explain how current social and economic conditions came to be, as well as how they might be improved. Brian also discusses the many initiatives Westminster Church has undertaken toward that goal.
      Brian Hamilton discusses moving to Washington, DC and living and raising a family in Southwest; his work with the Westminster Presbyterian Church; the history of the neighborhood and the church; the church's involvement in the Southwest community; urban renewal, gentrification, and changes and issues in the neighborhood; and his thoughts and hopes related to the future of the area.
    - Bruce Kellogg Interview, 2017-09-19; dcpl_dcohc003_06.mp3
      Bruce is a retired 35-year resident of Southwest. He has traveled extensively in maritime service and with the Peace Corps and USAID. He married an Afghan during his travels, and his dual-nationality household has been a stable presence in the Carrollsburg neighborhood, with his wife and children also very active in local and international volunteer work.
      Bruce Kellogg discusses what brought him to Washington, DC and his time spent living in Southwest; his time spent working and traveling with international agencies and organizations such as the Peace Corps, USAID, and the United Seaman's Service; how he met his wife and the experience of raising their three children in DC; development plans for the neighborhood and residents' reactions; some of his hobbies and volunteer efforts; and the rivers and waterfront areas in Southwest.
    - David Ehrlich Interview, 2017-09-25; dcpl_dcohc003_07.mp3
      David is an 80-year-old resident of Southwest. He is retired, but performs chamber music locally and is, with his wife, very active in local events and the arts. In this interview he highlights some of the changes Southwest has seen over his 38 years living there as well as the many reasons he prefers living in DC to other urban and suburban areas.
      David Ehrlich discusses what brought him to Washington, DC and the Southwest neighborhood, in particular; his work history and experience as a pianist and chamber music performer; his thoughts on the changes, amenities, and construction and redevelopment in the area; and his and his wife Barbara's travels and involvement in the community.
    - Thelma D. Jones Interview, 2017-09-26; dcpl_dcohc003_08.mp3